Finding Aid for the Pan-American Exposition Company Records, 1899-1908 (bulk 1899-1902)
Buffalo History Museum. Research Library
Pan-American Exposition Company Records
1899 - 1908
1899 - 1902
Mss. C65-7
Pan-American Exposition Company (Buffalo, N.Y.)
5 boxes, 36 oversize volumes (14.5 linear feet)
The records of Pan-American Exposition Company consist primary of the company's activities between 1899 and 1908.
The Buffalo History Museum 1 Museum Court Buffalo, NY 14216 Phone: 716-873-9644 ext. 306 Fax: 716-873-8754 Email: library@buffalohistory.org URI: http://www.buffalohistory.org
Administrative Information
Terms of Access
The Pan-American Exposition Company Records, 1899-1908, are open for research.
Administrative Information
Acquisition Information
Division of Ethnology and Archaeology exhibit records unknown; unknown; 0000/00/00; none
U.S. Government Building guard orders and list unknown; unknown; 0000/00/00; none
Women's Administration Building visitor register unknown - found in newspaper room; unknown; 0000/00/00; 65-114
Director-General's report Fleming, Edwin; gift; 1920/12/00; 28018
Board of Director's minutes, v. 1, 2, 4 Fleming, Edwin; gift; 1920/10/00; 27928-30
Accruals and Additions
No further accruals are expected to this collection.
Historical Note
The Pan-American Exposition Company was incorporated under the Pan-American bill signed by Governor Theodore Roosevelt on Jan. 20, 1899. The bill became Chapter 2 of the New York State laws of 1899.
Twenty-five of the more than 300 incorporators were elected to serve three-year terms as members of the board of directors. The board was charged with making and amending Exposition by-laws, electing a president, ten or more vice-presidents, a secretary, a treasurer, creating committees as needed, and filling all vacant positions. The board also formed an executive committee, and appointed a director general, an auditor, and a board of women managers.
The board of directors elected John G. Milburn president, and appointed William Buchanan director-general. The following committees were created: finance; concessions and exhibits; transportation; publicity; law and insurance; foreign relations; and printing and supplies.
Scope and Content Note
Minutes of the Board of Directors, 1899-1909; financial records, including cash books, ledgers, a record of insurance, and auditors' memoranda; site selection records; an index to exhibits; construction field books; Board of Women Managers' minutes and visitor register; correspondence, reports, and memoranda of the Director-General; also budgets, estimates, and contracts of the Director-General; a letter to Roswell Park concerning the operation on President McKinley; Press Dept. and Bureau of Information reports; Division of Ethnology and Archaeology visitor registers and exhibit records; New York State Building visitor registers; and U.S. Government Building guard orders and personnel lists.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in eleven series:
I. Board of Directors
II. Joint Committee of Architects and Engineers
III. Committee on Exhibits
IV. Board of Women Managers
V. Director-General
VI. Medical Director
VII. Committee of Audit
VIII. Dept. of Works
IX. Division of Ethnology and Archaeology
X. New York State Building
XI. U.S. Government Building.
Container List
- Board of Directors 1899-1909, I.
  Arranged in chronologically with two subseries Treasurer, 1899-1908 and Secretary, undated.
  - Minutes March 6-December 5, 1899 (Box 1, Volume 1)
  - Minutes January 2-September 20, 1900 (Box 1, Volume 2)
  - Minutes April 2-August 27, 1901 (Box 1, Volume 3)
  - Minutes September 3, 1901-October 22, 1909 (Box 1, Volume 4)
  - Agreement with Bronson C. Rumsey, re excavations on leased land, 1900 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Treasurer, 1899-1908; I.A.
    - Mortgage bond resolutions, memoranda, 1900-1902 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Cash book, November. 2, 1901-November. 29, 1906 (Box 1, Volume 5)
    - Journal, April. 30. 1901-January. 1902 (Box 1, Volume 6)
    - Books of the Pan-American Exposition Company as per balance sheet at Nov. 2, 1901, journal, November 2, 1901-October 1908 (Box 1, Volume 7)
    - Construction ledger, June 20, 1899-June 30, 1903 (Box 1, Volume 8)
      Lists date, voucher no., what for, total, and includes the buildings, canals, docks, bridges, horses, wagons, plumbing, architectural services, railroads, etc.
    - Department ledger 1, April 27, 1899-April 30, 1901 (Box 1, Volume 9)
    - Department ledger 2, July 12, 1901-February 20, 1902 (Box 1, Volume 10)
    - Department ledger 3, June 1, 1901 - October 20, 1902 (Box 1, Volume 11)
      Include disbursements for salaries, advertising, carriage hire, entertainment, freight, express, laundry, publications, etc., for the various departments, bureaus and committees. They do not list exhibitors.
    - Ledger A, 1899-1900 (Box 1, Volume 12)
      Includes exhibitors and the buildings in which they exhibited.
    - Sub ledger, 1901-1902 (Box 1, Volume 13)
      Includes alphabetical index.
    - Voucher record no. 1, January 30, 1899 - January 1902 (Box 1, Volume 14)
    - Voucher record no. 2, October 3, 1901 - October 22, 1908 (Box 1, Volume 15)
      List date, no., in whose favor, what for, total, and figures for officers' salaries, general expenses, office furniture & equipment, plant, and the various departments, bureaus, and committees.
    - Check register no. 1, March 10, 1899 - September 27, 1901 (Box 1, Volume 16)
      Includes date, no., order of, for, charge, amount. Alphabetical by name.
    - Bond interest coupon book - 1st mortgage bond, nos. 1-5001 (Box 1, Volume 17)
    - Bond interest coupon book - 1st mortgage bond, nos. 5001-5825, and 2nd mortgage bond (Box 1, Volume 18)
  - Secretary, undated; I.B.
    - Stock book and subscribers' ledger no. 1, A-E (Box 1, Volume 19)
    - Stock book and subscribers' ledger no. 2, F-K (Box 1, Volume 20)
    - Stock book and subscribers' ledger no. 3, L-R (Box 1, Volume 21)
    - Stock book and subscribers' ledger no. 4, S-Z 1st call to 10th call (Box 1, Volume 22)
      Includes subscriber's name, date payment, balance. Alphabetical by name of subscriber.
    - Committee on Law and Insurance: record of insurance, 1899-1901 (Box 1, Volume 23)
- Joint Committee of Architects and Engineers, 1873-1899, II.
  - Minutes, March 26 - April 4, 1899 (Box 1, Volume 24)
    Includes evaluation of potential Exposition sites.
  - Memorandum to Executive Committee re selection of site and adoption of plot plans, March 31, 1899 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Report on sites, Apr. 5, 1899. Information on suggested sites. Cost of buildings, etc., at Chicago World's Columbian Exposition,1893. Statistics of various Expositions, 1873-1893. Plan of [Riverside] site.
  - Scrapbook, March 21 - May 13, 1899 (Box 1, Volume 25)
    Clippings re Joint Committee and site search.
- Committee on Exhibits, undated, III.
  - Index to exhibits (Box 2, Volume 26)
- Board of Women Managers, 1900-1901, IV.
  - Minutes, 1900-1901 (Box 2, Volume 27)
    Includes list of Applied Arts Section exhibitors and awards.
  - Minutes, Women's Administration Building visitor register, 1901 (Box 2, Volume 28)
- Director-General, 1899-1901; V.
  - Correspondence, 1899-1901 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Includes well rashes from heads of state.
  - Report, parts 1-4 (copy 1) (Box 2, Volume 29)
  - Report, parts 5-7 (Box 3, Volume 29)
    Includes sections on finances, construction, opening month, dedication, officers and committees, state and federal legislation, by-laws, juries and awards; also reports of exhibit divisions, and administrative bureaus and departments.
  - Report (copy 2); first part missing (Box 3, Volume 29)
  - Memoranda to Dept. of Works, 1899-1900 (Box 4, Volume 30)
    Addressed to Newcomb Carlton, Director of Works; most regard actions of the Executive Committee
  - Budgets, estimates and contracts, 1900-1901 (Box 4, Volume 31)
- Medical Director, 1901, VI.
  - Letter, Acting Deputy Nelson W. Wilson, to Roswell Park, re reception of, and operation on, President McKinley, September 6, 1901. (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Committee of Audit, July 23-November 12, 1902, VII.
  - Memoranda of action, July 23-November 12, 1902 (Box 4, Volume 32)
- Department of Works, 1900-1901; VIII.
  Contains construction field books.
  - Electricity Building, September 24, 1900 - April 25, 1901 (Box 4, Volume 33)
  - Restaurant, propylaea, and stadium, June 25, 1900 - November 30, 1900 (Box 4, Volume 34)
  - Stadium, restaurant, propylaea and pergolas, December. 1, 1900 - May 31, 1901 (Box 4, Volume 35)
  - Electric Tower, September 22, 1900 - May 30, 1901 (Box 4, Volume 36)
  - Electric Tower lumber, September 18 - November 5, 1900 (Box 5, Volume 37)
    Field books inscribed, "H.C. Parsons, Supt."
  - Ledger, 1901 Lists services such as sewer connections, cleaning, garbage collection, fire service, lighting, etc., performed for exhibitors and businesses by the Works Dept. (Box 5, Volume 38)
  - Bureau of Information report on accomplishments; includes expenses, undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Press Dept. (Bureau of Publicity) reports, 1901 Reports of Mark Bennett and Stephen W. Bolles, Superintendents. (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Division of Ethnology and Archaeology, 1991-1992; IX.
  - Description of Ethnology Building, 1902 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    Includes report on mounds, office rules, inventory of office furniture and supplies, report re visitor registers, report to Director-General, and list of miscellaneous items.
  - Payroll, 1901 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Exhibits (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Exhibit labels (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Admissions (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Visitors' cards, A-K (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Visitors' cards, L-Z (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Application for exhibit space book (Box 5, Volume 39)
    Includes description of articles (number, kind), space desired inside building (floor space, wall space, wall space in art room, table cases, didactic cases), space desired outside building (length, width)
  - Visitor register, May 1 - June 23, 1901 (Box 5, Volume 40)
  - Visitor register, June 23 - July 25, 1901 (Box 5, Volume 41)
  - Visitor register, July 25 - August 22, 1901 (Box 5, Volume 42)
  - Visitor register, August 22 - September 17, 1901 (Box 5, Volume 43)
  - Visitor register, September 17-November 19, 1901 (Box 5, Volume 44)
    These include some brief comments
- New York State Building, 1991; X.
  Comments not included.
  - Visitor register, May 20 - July 25, 1901 (Box 5, Volume 45)
  - Visitor register, July 25 - August 14, 1901 (Box 5, Volume 46)
  - Visitor register, August 15 - August 30, 1901 (Box 5, Volume 47)
  - Visitor register, August 30 - September 17, 1901 (Box 5, Volume 48)
  - Visitor register, September 17 - October 4, 1901 (Box 5, Volume 49)
  - Visitor register, October 5 - October 19, 1901 (Box 5, Volume 50)
  - Visitor register, October 19 - November 2, 1901 (Box 5, Volume 51)
- U.S. Government Building, undated, XI.
  - Guard orders and department personnel lists. (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Series I: Board of Directors
  - Subseries A: Treasurer
  - Subseries B: Secretary
- Series II: Joint Committee of Architects and Engineers
- Series III: Committee on Exhibits
- Series IV: Board of Woman Managers
- Series V: Director-General
- Series VI: Medical Director
- Series VII: Committee of Audit
- Series VIII: Dept. of Works
- Series IX: Division of Ethnology and Archaeology
- Series X: New York State Building
- Series XI: U.S. Government Building
Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog.
Contributors
Park, Roswell, 1852-1914; Buffalo History Museum
Subject Terms
McKinley, William, 1843-1901--Assassination; Pan-American Exposition (1901: Buffalo, N.Y.); Exhibitions--New York (State)--Buffalo
Genre Terms
Ledgers (account books); Visitors' books